We all sit down and the president says,
"Well, now what do we do?" And then
everybody turns and looks at me. I'm 25
years old. They're asking for my advice
[music] on issues of war and peace. I
rose up to be the chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
[music]
after the 9/11 attacks. December of 2007
I gave a nationally televised interview
to ABC News [music] in which I said that
the CIA was torturing its prisoners. The
Obama administration secretly reopened
the case against me. They charged me
with five felonies for blowing the
whistle on the torture program.
>> And curious and [music] all based off
everything that you know and what you've
done, what do you see most people get
wrong when it comes to trying to [music]
influence someone to get something from?
>> I'm always surprised at how many people
think that
>> What are the fastest ways to deepen
rapport and trust with someone?
>> You try to quickly assess what it is
this guy
>> John,
welcome to the podcast.
>> Thank you.
>> You spent 2 years in jail. Nearly a
3-year sentence, wasn't it? Without
>> Yeah, it was a 2 and 1/2 year sentence.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Uh for blowing the whistle on
things CIA were doing.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh and since then they've made your life
kind of difficult and life's changed a
lot.
>> to.
>> They've tried to.
For the people who might have maybe
maybe they've seen your face, maybe
they've seen some clips, or maybe they
don't even know who you are.
>> Right.
>> How would you introduce yourself? Who
Who were you before
all of that happened?
>> Sure. I'm John Kiriakou. I was a CIA
officer for
oh, about 14 and 1/2 years. And um I
rose up to be the chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
after the 9/11 attacks.
Um had actually some even more senior
jobs after that. But um I objected to
the CIA's torture program. Uh at first
internally and later on in public to ABC
News in 2007. December of 2007 I gave a
nationally televised uh interview to ABC
News in which I said that the CIA was
torturing its prisoners. Funny enough,
the Bush administration elected to not
prosecute me because
it is a crime
to classify a crime.
And they said that torture was a crime
and so blowing the whistle on it was not
a crime even if the the program had been
classified.
The Obama administration under the under
the leadership of John Brennan
however
uh asked the Justice Department to
secretly reopen the case against me.
They investigated me for three more
years and then finally charged me with
five felonies including three counts of
espionage for blowing the whistle on the
torture program.
>> In in that period were you
were you working with them or did you
quit and then
>> Oh, no, no, no. I I left in 2004.
>> Oh, okay. So, you were out before you
came public.
>> Yeah, I kept waiting for somebody to say
something about this illegal clearly
illegal program.
And nobody did and then finally I did.
And um and then in the meantime I went
into the private sector for 4 years. I
left there and then I went to the I was
the chief investigator on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee for 2 and
1/2 years and then went into business
for myself and that's when
you know, they came down on me.
>> So, so you spent nearly 15 years um not
just as some sort of by the sounds of it
some sort of lower level. You're you're
a quite you were doing some some wild
[__]
>> Oh, yeah.
>> And from what I've seen and putting the
research together on you is you spent a
lot of time essentially
on the ground getting people to know
you, like you, and trust you enough
where they would give up secrets where
they're committing treason or on
country.
>> Mhm.
>> Um I really want to focus a lot on the
topic of influence and and that whole
subject. And I'm curious to know based
off everything you know and what you've
done, what do you see most people get
wrong when it comes to trying to
influence someone to get something from
them?
>> You know, I'm always surprised at how
many people think
that the CIA uses coercion
to get people to give up secrets.
Coercion doesn't work. If I come up to
you and I say,
you know, "Listen, give me your secrets
or I'm going to
you know, punch you in the face."
You're going to tell me to go fly a
kite.
>> Mhm.
>> But, if I
befriend you and I
you know, spend money on you and we
vacation together and our wives become
friends and our kids become friends and
you know, we really become close.
You're going to do it just because we're
friends.
You know, if if we've been friends for a
year and we we took our families on a
ski trip together and we go out for
guys' night and go have a couple of
beers
and and we're really close.
And I say, "Morgan, listen, I
I could really use the
I'm having some trouble at work and
one thing that was real that would
really help me is I could really use the
plans to that new Russian tank
that you have access to. That would so
help me out. I would really be
grateful." You're going to do it because
you like me, because we're friends, not
cuz I've threatened you
or I have you know, pictures of you with
a prostitute and I'm threatening to show
your wife. That that's not going to get
me anywhere.
>> But, would you you would have all of
these things
>> No, no.
>> Do you not have a plan B, C, D?
>> You don't even You don't even go down
that road. Nothing good is going to come
of that.
No. The Russians do it. The Israelis do
it.
We don't do it.
It's wasted time.
>> So, cuz I'm I'm trying to put myself in
that position. I'm just I'm picturing
myself with one of my best friends.
Known him for over a decade. If I was
working If I had access to secret
intelligence, I'm working with the
Australian government.
And he said that to me, I'd be like,
bro, I love you.
>> But it's not going to happen.
>> No way. Yeah.
>> See, and I would say the same thing
because you and I are not recruitable.
>> Right.
>> But
I haven't targeted you because you're a
great guy. I've targeted you because you
have access, but you also have a
gambling problem. Or a drug problem, or
an alcohol problem, or maybe your wife's
got cancer and you would really, really
like for her to be treated at the Mayo
Clinic. Or you're not making any money,
but you really want your kid to go to a
great American university. I'm I'm
looking for a a hook, a vulnerability.
It's not just cuz you're a great guy. I
don't care if you're a great guy. I'm
going to pretend that you're a great guy
if you're not.
But I'm also looking for that
vulnerability that I can latch on to.
>> So not everyone is recruitable.
>> No.
>> Does it sound
>> Most people, I would say, are not
recruitable.
>> What would you do if you're up against
someone who you've been found to
they're unrecruitable.
But you needed to get access to
something from them.
>> I'd break into their office and steal
it.
>> Okay.
Right. Okay.
Cuz I mean, there's so much I want to
unpack here. Um
from your recommendation, actually, I
saw you to say on another podcast,
you're like, um Homeland.
>> Yeah.
>> Did I can't remember what you said. Did
you say that was quite accurate?
>> Quite accurate. The only thing that's
not accurate about Homeland is if you go
nuts while you're overseas, they're
going to bring you home. They're not
going to just say, "Ah, it's kind of a
shame she went nuts. Well, let's leave
her in the field, let her do do her
thing."
>> Little dramatic.
>> Yeah, it's it's too much.
>> Cuz I I've been I've been watching it
and uh man, I'm like hooked. I'm like,
this is so fascinating, but I think I'm
fascinated because I'm like, I could
absolutely see how real this could be.
>> Mhm.
>> Um like, but what I've seen is
um because I've been so fascinated on
the the topic of influence just for such
long time and
um what I've seen from that show
is they'll get whatever they want
because
agencies like CIA have access to I mean
anything they can get like they can hack
in the phones, they can spy on all this
stuff. So
>> Anything your heart desires.
>> So so when it comes down to getting you
to do something, what commonly comes up
is essentially blackmail.
They're like, "Well, we have pictures of
you going to this brothel. You sure you
don't want to give us this or we're
going to go to this?" And what
So this is that's for TV.
>> Mhm.
That's for TV.
>> Interesting, I feel like Santa's been um
I just found out Santa's not real.
>> Yeah, sorry. [laughter]
You know, when I first joined, one of my
instructors told told me that, you know,
back in the in the day, in the 50s, the
60s, the 70s, yes, they used to try
that.
But he told me that one time
one of his
superiors, I guess back in the
back in the 70s, I suppose,
there was this cleric
and they set him up with a prostitute
and they took pictures through, you
know, a pinhole with a a pinhole camera
of him, you know, humping the
prostitute. And then they went to him
and they said, "We want X Y Z
information." And they laid out all
these pictures of him with the
prostitute and he said, "Ooh, I'll take
that in an 8 by 10. And give me two of
those in 5 by 7. And how about some
wallet sizes for these?" He's like, "Get
the [__] out of here."
And they just made a policy decision
that this doesn't work. These these just
naked threats, no pun intended, they
they don't work.
And so
they just sort of revamped the way
approaches were made.
>> Mhm. How how did it not work? Cuz I I
would imagine
Well, I mean, every everyone's just got
their life, right?
>> Look at it this way. Look at it this
way.
You get caught with a prostitute. You
have two choices.
You can
confess to your wife,
>> Mhm.
>> maybe jeopardize your marriage, maybe
get a slap in the face.
Or you can commit treason and risk
execution. So which one are you going to
pick?
>> Yeah, I guess that makes sense.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, so when everything's up against
I mean, that's the worst case is what
you're asking them to do.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh,
okay. So,
so what you're sort of saying it's it's
it's a complete other approach. It's
it's
find someone from the get-go who could
possibly be recruitable, develop a
strong bond, strong communication,
strong Sorry. Strong relationship with
them.
Get them to the point where they like
you enough where they'll just want to do
you a favor.
>> Mhm.
Look at it this way, too.
The CIA, any intelligence service, has
this thing called the asset acquisition
cycle.
It's spot, assess, develop, recruit.
So, I go to some diplomatic cocktail
party.
And and I spot you. And I say, "Hi, I'm
John. What's your name?" We exchange
business cards.
You work for the Canadian Embassy? Nice
to meet you. And I walk on to the next
guy. You work for the Russian Embassy?
Or the Chinese? Or the Cuban?
Okay, I'm going to maybe invite you to
lunch. So, I've spotted you. I've
assessed your access to information that
I might that I might want.
And then, I begin the development phase.
This is the longest phase. It can go
months, it can go
years in some cases. But, in that
development phase, I'm going to try to
assess if you have any vulnerabilities.
And I said it as I said a few minutes
ago, a vulnerability doesn't have to be
a bad thing. A vulnerability might mean
you just really, really love your kids.
And you want the best for your kids. And
maybe the best means going to UCLA or
Harvard. Right? And your kid's not going
to get into Harvard.
I can get your kid into Harvard. And
I'll pay for it.
So, I'm developing you.
Do you like to drink? Do you cheat on
your wife? You know, maybe you and I
go out drinking or we go to Vegas for
the weekend or we figure something out,
something that you really like to do.
And I can observe you over that period
and look for that hook.
>> Mhm.
>> Now, 95 In 95% of cases and studies
internal studies have been done about
this at the agency, 95% of the cases the
hook is money.
Right? You want money. I have money.
I'll give the I'll give you the money if
you give me the information. It's just a
contractual arrangement. Very simple.
But the other 5% is kind of interesting.
Um in some cases it's excitement. You
know, you've watched Homeland, you've
seen the James Bond movies. You want a
piece of that excitement, that
adrenaline rush of being clandestine.
You'd be surprised the people who are
just doing it for the rush.
>> Yeah.
>> And then the others are
um
ideology. You really, really love the
United States. And you want to do it
just to be helpful to the United States
or revenge.
You do it because you got passed over
for promotion and by God you're going to
screw your boss
by volunteering to the Americans.
But 95% of the time it's simply cash for
information.
>> Is this where you have a picture of them
on the board and you're mapping out
everything about them? Is this like
where where
where you're doing like analysis on
someone and trying to really figure out
like pro So, profiling somebody?
>> Yes.
>> So
>> That's exactly what we do.
>> Can you walk us through this? So, is I'm
imagining this would be Well, walk me
through actually profiling someone
because this is so fascinating.
>> So, every year the CIA and every
intelligence service begins the year
with something called an operating
directive.
What is it that we want to collect this
year?
What is it that's going to provide the
most help to the the formation, the
formulation of American foreign policy.
Okay, so we're interested in China,
Russia, North Korea, Iran, terrorism,
proliferation,
whatever.
And you rank these things, right?
There's tier zero, which means, you
know,
war is imminent.
Tier one is going to be China, Russia,
Iran.
Tier two might be, I'm making this up,
Cuba, who knows, Venezuela, whatever.
Down to tier five, which is
nobody cares about it, you know, EU
grain harvests, nobody cares.
So, um,
with this in mind, you know, as you go
out to this cocktail party, what the
operating directive is, you know what
you need to collect on. So, I go to a I
go to a cocktail party and I say hi to
you and you say hi to me and we shake
hands and I hand you my card, I'm John
Kiriakou from the American Embassy. You
say, "Oh, I work at the at the port."
I don't care about the port.
But I say, "Oh my gosh, that sounds so
interesting. What do you do at the port?
Oh, I always love ports. It's always so
exciting, ships coming in, going out,
all over the world, very international."
I'm just making all this up
to engage you.
And you say that there's a ship coming
in from wherever and it has a
shipment of this chemical.
I'm not a chemist. I don't know what
that means.
But when I go back to the embassy, I'm
going to say, "I met this guy. He
appears to be this age. He's this tall.
He's, you know, this weight. He has
brown eyes. He has brown hair and he
works at the port. Here's his name.
Here's his title. Please let me know if
you have anything in the files, which
they likely will not." And I say, "He
mentioned that there's a ship coming in
and it has this chemical on it."
And then they come back to me and say,
"That's the precursor chemical for
cocaine."
So I say, "Aha, that I'm interested in."
So I call you and I say, "Hey, it was so
great meeting you the other day.
I would hope that you would allow me to
take you to dinner."
And nine times out of 10 you're going to
say yes. And we get together for dinner.
And I tell you
how much I enjoyed our conversation. And
this thing at the port is so
fascinating. What do you like to do in
your spare time?
And you tell me something that you're
interested in.
I sort of gauge
where you would like to see this
relationship go. Um maybe you mention,
"Ah, I've been at the port 10 years. I
haven't been promoted in 10 years."
Okay, that's important information for
me.
Um
so I
look for ways that I can help you.
Maybe you would love love love to go to
the United States on vacation. No
problem. I can have the visa ready in
the morning.
Um maybe, like I said, your wife is sick
or your child is sick or your child's
graduating from high school, wants to go
to school in the States. Or, you know,
you've
your car broke down. I mean, this
happened to me once. Like my car broke
down. I've had this car for 10 years. I
have literally no way to get to work.
I'm happy to buy you a car
if you give me an hour in your code
room.
So you try to quickly
assess
what it is this guy wants or needs
and what information he might have
access to that he'd be willing to give
up.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay. So you look So
you're building rapport. There There's
so many avenues I want to get down. I
like to sort of go like linear through
our thing. So like let's say
um
so you're at a cocktail party. You're at
a networking event. You find somebody
you're talking.
How do you
cuz even for myself, I'm one of those
extroverts introverts. I'm extrovert
when I want to be.
>> Yes.
>> And I can quickly my battery just I can
be at a thing I'll be like I'm bored.
Get me out. I can mean I can literally
be in a conversation with someone
know that I should really talk to these
people but my face just says like [__]
off.
>> Mhm.
>> How how do you first
especially for the introverts who are
watching this, how do you first get
yourself into a position where you can
be somewhat interested even though your
brain's kind of saying like I'm I just
don't want I just don't want to talk to
these people.
>> What's up legend? Real quick, you're
listening to this podcast clearly
because you're a big dreamer, you're a
big thinker and you want to achieve
massive freaking things on this planet.
What I know from my experience and
interviewing so many successful people,
one of the fastest ways to achieve what
it is you want is to be in the
environment with those who are like you
and learning from people and where you
want to get to. And that's why every
single year I run an event called
DreamFest. This is our fifth year of
doing it. We've had thousands and
thousands of guests in the past. We've
had wicked speakers. Last year we had
Dan Martell and this year we're even
going bigger. And every year we bring
the best speakers from the industry to
help you level up your skill set and
your mindset so you can create your
dream life. It's two full days live on
the Gold Coast here in Australia but
this year we're even going to have a
virtual option. So head to the link in
the description of this episode and
you're going to find all the information
you need. Get yourself a ticket and I
can't wait to see you in August at
DreamFest.
>> Listen, listen, it's it's all an acting
job.
>> Okay.
>> It really is. First of all, you cannot
be a CIA operations officer and be an
introvert.
>> Oh, really?
>> The two are are incompatible with one
another. You have to genuinely love
doing this.
>> Okay.
>> I remember working for a guy, he was a
fantastic station chief. He was I mean,
he could have recruited me. I so enjoyed
just being around him. He was funny and
full of great stories and just a great
leader, a manager. But he used to say,
"Listen, you going to this party
tonight?" Yep, I'm going to the party.
He said, "I want you to show me 20
business cards tomorrow."
And I'd say, "Okay."
And so, I would go from person to person
to person, make sure I got 20 business
cards or 25.
>> Mhm.
>> And then, he would say,
"Not interested, not interested, not
interested. Ah, this guy, yeah, we'd be
interested in him."
And so, I would,
you know, take the five or the 10 out of
the 20
that we might have operational interest
in
and call and say, "Hey, I'd love to take
you to lunch. I had such a nice time,
you know, in our conversation the other
day."
>> Okay.
So, okay, so we you go back before you'd
have your next encounter. Are you
already starting to profile this person
from what you already know, or is it
just is the is the intention to set the
next encounter to start deepening the
relationship and building more trust?
>> Oh,
yes and yes. So,
these these things are not mutually
exclusive. You've got to be
working on multiple people at any given
time, and you're going to be in
different phases of that relationship at
any given time. Maybe I just met you
last night at a cocktail party, but this
other guy I met
3 weeks ago, and we're already into the
relationship, and there's another guy I
met 6 months ago, and he and his wife
are having dinner with my wife and me,
you know, in some little out-of-the-way
place so I can make him feel at ease.
So, you're going to be at different
phases
all at the same time, and trying to keep
five, six, eight people straight in your
mind.
And then,
what you do to to make that easier
is I wouldn't even wait for the next day
to write this up and send it to
headquarters. I would go right from the
dinner
through it through a surveillance
detection route
back to the embassy, and I would write
it up that night. And it didn't matter
if I needed to be at the embassy until
1:00 in the morning. I was going to make
sure that this information got back
ASAP, so I didn't miss any of it.
>> Mhm. Okay. So, so walk me through this
this mice framework then. So, cuz what
I've sort of got so far is number one,
be extroverted sometimes even if you've
got to act it.
>> Yep.
>> Uh network with as many people, find who
you're actually interested to pursue
another conversation.
Develop a relationship, but what you're
really looking for is where is a gap?
Where is a vulnerability they have? What
is something that they really need? Cuz
maybe they want it for pleasure or maybe
they want it to avoid suffering. Um so,
for the listeners, walk us through what
does mice stand for?
And how why why do you use that?
>> mice is not a CIA acronym.
>> Okay.
>> That's just been kind of made up by the
public that's interested in this kind of
thing.
>> Interesting.
>> Um
like I said, you can use wow, so many
different
tools to recruit somebody. With M, money
uh being the most important one. Now, if
you've if you're a guy who's got, you
know, access to the local Communist
Party,
that's moderately interesting to me.
It's
not terribly important. That might be
worth a couple thousand bucks a month.
If you're going to give me Osama bin
Laden's location,
that's going to be worth 25 million.
And I'm happy to give it to you in gold,
in diamonds, uh in cash.
Uh we can set up a bank account for you.
We can give it to you in land, in any
country that you want to to go to.
We can work something out. But, it's
going to be different for every single
person.
It's going to be tailored.
Um
it's not
unheard of
for somebody to want the money, let's
say, in diamonds.
And so,
we've got a relationship with a guy who
has access to the diamonds.
I'm going to get, you know, 30 different
diamonds in all different sizes and
colors and clarity and shape. And I'm
going to give you the diamonds. And
then,
if you need to cash in a diamond,
here's a phone number that you call,
and you ask for Mike. And the person's
going to say that Mike's not in right
now. May I take a message? And you say,
"Yeah, tell him that uh his Uncle Chuck
uh says hello, and he hopes to see him
at Christmas."
And that means meet me in 24 hours at
the coffee shop at such and such a
you know, an intersection.
And
an officer will show up with an envelope
of cash.
You cash in one of your diamonds.
And then, we just wait for the next
encounter.
>> Mhm.
So, I'm I'm trying to imagine So, I
guess everyone's different. Would Would
it be right by saying
cuz I'm shocked that money is the number
one.
>> Are you?
>> But I'm also not. Because
>> Don't be.
>> As I was thinking cuz I I
>> People are greedy bastards.
>> Then, am I right by saying that cuz
probably the people CIA would be
recruiting
are probably not wealthy people.
>> Correct. They're mostly government
employees.
>> Yeah. So, they're all quite underpaid.
So, they would take cash.
>> Sure.
>> Yeah. So, what what about for someone
who
And I was actually also thinking this.
I'm like, am I motivated by my money? I
I think to some degree. And what I was
what I was thinking is
it would it would come down to how much
and in which time frame.
Cuz that's that's how like the mind
works. Because if somebody said,
"I'll give you
a million dollars for doing this."
If I get a million dollars straight
away, that's exciting. But if I got a
million dollars spread out over
a year or something like that. I'd be
like, "Ah,
I mean, I could make that a you know
you know what I mean? So
>> But if you're a government employee
>> Yeah.
>> in some third world country
>> Money's everything.
>> making 10 or 12,000 dollars a year.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah. And I'm offering you 50,000
like right now.
50,000 is not a lot of money for the
CIA, but it's life-changing
for you.
>> Mhm.
>> If you're, you know, some Afghan
functionary in the government or, you
know, from whatever country it's
life-changing.
>> Mhm.
>> You can pay off your entire family's
debts. You can buy a piece of land.
>> Yeah. So what are the other ones then?
So if you if you're trying to scope
somebody out, you're like, "That person
money's not going to sway them."
What would be my other approach?
>> Well, like I said, here early on in the
relationship, you're trying to determine
what the vulnerability is. Oftentimes,
at least in the course of my career, it
was medical care.
I had a guy volunteer once
because his wife had breast cancer.
>> Mhm.
>> And this was a we were living in a third
world country and
the medical care was substandard.
And this guy really loved his wife.
And he's like, "Can you help her?"
Like, "Yeah, of course I can.
We'll get her to the Mayo Clinic
and uh and she'll have the best cancer
treatment that's available anywhere."
And that's what we did.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
>> I've heard I've heard people talk about
So you even mentioned before. So
ideology
>> Mhm.
>> um
Coercion, I think people talk about, but
you kind of ruled that one out. So
you're saying it's completely cuz I was
thinking about I'm like
I
I I think the only time you'd ever
really use this if you never wanted to
ever have that person ever like you ever
again.
>> Or look at it this way.
If somebody tried to use coercion
against me,
>> Mhm.
>> I might say, "Okay, meet me at 3:00 in
the morning at this intersection."
And then I'd blow his brains out.
Because if he's going to try to ruin my
life and put my life and my freedom in
jeopardy, he's going to die.
>> Mhm. So, talk to me about ideology then.
I mean, sorry, I ideology and the the
ego.
Like how how are you I I I guess I'm
trying to just sort of dissect like if
I'm I'm going to sit down and read
somebody. I I guess you you may have one
approach cuz you said before, I don't
have a plan B or a C. So, you're kind of
going in
asking someone of something, but you
must be so certain that that is going to
work on them.
>> Well,
yes, but let me explain. So, there there
is such a thing called a cold pitch.
Cold pitches almost never ever work.
That is, I knock on your door, I say,
"I'm Bob from the CIA and I know who you
are and I need this information from
you." That never works.
First of all, maybe I'm not Bob from the
CIA, maybe I'm Igor from the KGB.
Or maybe I'm from your own
police force and you're trying to entrap
me.
And so, usually people run screaming
from the room, they call the cops, they
call their service, you get expelled,
it's a big
big kerfuffle.
So,
cold pitches don't work. So, normally,
you work on a person for long enough
that you know they're going to say yes
to the pitch. And you know exactly what
it is that they're going to want from
you. Right? You never go in unprepared.
I I had a I had a station chief once
tell me that in the in the 25 plus years
he was at the CIA, he never had a target
say no.
And I can tell you in my 15 years, I
never had a target say no. Never.
Because if they say no, you're in a heap
of trouble. You're probably going to get
expelled from that country. Because if
they say no to you, they're probably
going to report you to their version of
the FBI.
And then it's going to be an
international incident.
So you have to be 100% sure
that they're just as into this as you
are. And this is going to be a mutually
beneficial relationship.
>> What are the fastest ways to
deepen rapport and trust with someone?
Cuz this is the thing that
there's some people I can connect with
and like instantly hit it off.
And I think it just comes down to if we
are naturally a similar personality
type.
And there's some people
I'm trying to connect with and I'm like,
this is just so they're just such a odd
personality or they're nothing like me
and I can feel this it's just like I'm I
can't go anywhere with this person. And
obviously with especially podcasting,
there's a bunch of guests that I meet
and I'm like, I stay really good friends
with them. There's a few guests I meet
and I'm like, ah just
I wouldn't talk to them outside the
episode. Um
is there a way around that internally?
>> Yeah.
>> Again, you are an actor.
>> Mhm.
>> You have to be an actor. And so even if
you're not connecting with somebody, by
God you better make it look like you're
connecting with them.
I I've told this story before where I
was instructed to target a
foreign diplomat.
And so
I did some light surveillance on him and
I learned that he would go to the same
coffee shop every day, 7 days a week.
9:00 in the morning he's at the coffee
shop. So one Saturday I would went to
his coffee shop and I bumped into him
and I was like, "Oh my gosh, what a
small world. Hey, how are you? It's good
to see you again."
And um I asked him if I could sit with
him. So I sat with him and we sat and
had a conversation,
and um drank our coffee.
And it became clear to me that he in
this conversation that he was gay.
And he was deeply closeted.
>> How did you discover that?
>> I just had a gut feeling.
And he he made a complaint in that
conversation that he had been passed
over for promotion.
And he made it sound
like even if he wasn't gay,
his superiors believed he was gay.
And I thought, "Well, they know him
better than I do. So, if they think he's
gay, he's probably gay." So, I reported
back, "He's gay."
And
headquarters said, "We want you to
pretend that you're gay."
And so, I said, "Okay."
So,
I call him back.
We end up going to dinner, then we go to
lunch, then we go to dinner again, and
then I got two tickets for a show, and
we went to the show, and went out for
sushi afterwards, and
and this went on for months.
And
he
he felt comfortable enough to complain
to me about the
the system in his foreign ministry, this
the promotion system in his foreign
ministry. I learned a lot.
And I was reporting everything back to
headquarters.
>> This was in Pakistan?
>> Oh, no, no. I I can't say where it was.
>> So, it wasn't in Pakistan, no.
So, um
it got to the point where
I've told this story before, and people
have taken this to be a joke, and
they've made memes and clips, and I'm
speaking in a funny voice. It was It was
very serious.
He He invited me to dinner at his
apartment one night. So, I went to his
apartment, we had dinner, and then he
leaned in to kiss me.
And I wasn't
I was momentarily distracted, and so
instinctively I backed off like this.
And he said, "Oh my god, I'm so sorry. I
thought you were gay." And I was like,
"Oh my god, I just screwed this up." And
I said,
"I am gay.
I'm just not into hairy guys."
>> [laughter]
>> And he's like, "Oh, I'm okay. Okay." And
I said, "Oh, I'm so sorry. I've led you
on." He said, "No, no. I think you're
great. I'm glad we're friends." I'm
like, "Oh my god, I think you're great,
too.
But we're not going to be a a couple."
And it was cool because he respected me.
And
in the end, he gave me everything that I
asked for
because
he was upset that he kept getting passed
over for promotion. And he did it out of
a sense of revenge.
But he trusted me enough
to give it to me.
>> Okay. And so my whole understanding with
developing and building rapport, it's a
lot of, you know, mirroring and matching
and blah blah blah.
Does it get any deeper than that of like
developing How can I develop deeper
trust to the point where someone's like,
"I I just feel like I can tell you
anything. I feel like I've known you for
so long."
>> Oh my god, you you read psychology books
in your spare time.
And the guy mentions offhandedly that he
likes fishing, you go learn how to fish
like well.
Or he likes,
uh, you know, cricket, you learn the
intricacies of cricket. You have a
favorite team.
You can speak authoritatively about
cricket and the history of cricket.
Or Broadway or soccer or
whatever he happens to be interested in,
you immerse yourself
in this.
You know, [snorts] a couple a couple
bosses I've had over the years have paid
me some real compliments. One of them
said, I was a brand new analyst. I'd
been on the job like 6 months. And I was
actually offended by this at first cuz I
I misunderstood it.
But my boss said, you know, you would be
a really terrific case officer. And I
was like, why? I'm not a good enough
analyst? Are you insulting me?
>> What's the difference between the two?
>> An analyst sits in a cubicle and thinks
the big thoughts and writes papers.
>> And that's what you were doing most of?
>> At at in the beginning of my career.
>> Okay.
>> Case officers recruiting spies to steal
secrets.
And so, he said, no, what I mean is
you're extroverted, you're a nice guy,
and people like to be around you, which
had never even occurred to me.
But it planted a seed in my mind that
maybe I will try operations. Maybe I
would be good at operations. And it
turned out that I was good at
operations. And then later in my career
when I had proven myself as an effective
operations officer
I recruited a guy
who was so sensitive that I couldn't
meet him in the country that I recruited
him in.
And so headquarters said
fly him back to Washington.
You fly a different way back to
Washington.
And we'll meet him here.
So we met him in a hotel here in
Washington.
And I invited my boss
and a senior operations officer
and the senior analyst
to come to the hotel and just sit. And I
mean, technically it was a debriefing,
but what it really was was a
get-to-know-you kind of session.
And so he said the the source said
uh you know, this is my first time in
the United States and and I hope I have
a couple of days built in because I'd
like to go to New York and I've never,
you know
seen a Broadway show. I'd love to see a
Broadway show. And I said, "Oh, listen,
Aida just opened on Broadway." I had
just read a review in the New York
Times. "Aida just opened on Broadway.
Elton John did the
did all of the music. He scored it. And
I forget who was the the lead actress
and
the New York Times raved about it." I
said, "I'll get us tickets. We'll go to
New York together."
And he said, "Tell me about this sport
you have here, this baseball. What is
this?" I said, "Oh, we just got a team
in Washington, the Washington Nationals.
We're not very good, but it's but it's
fun and we're going to play the Yankees
and the Yankees are a legendary team.
I'll get us tickets. We'll go after
dinner."
And there was something else that we
talked about in that meeting. And
afterwards, my boss came to me
and he said, "I have never seen someone
speak so authoritatively
on such disparate issues
as you did today. And then you did a
substantive debriefing."
And I said, "You know what it is? I love
this job.
That's what it is.
I don't even feel like this is work.
I couldn't wait to get to the office in
the morning
just to see what I had missed while I
was sleeping."
>> Mhm.
>> And so, you either have it or you don't
have it.
And if you don't have it, cut your
losses and go find something that's
going to make you happy.
>> If you were to have to recruit me now
into doing something based off like you
barely even know me or actually I don't
know if you scoped me out or anything.
Um what vulnerabilities do you see in
me? What would be your angle?
>> I'm not seeing any yet. You did mention
that you um went skiing
uh recently. And so, I would press you
on that just to see where you've gone
skiing, how talented you are at skiing.
I'm actually not very good, but you
know, if you're around, there are a lot
of places we could go skiing. Have you
ever been to Park City? Have you ever
been to, you know, Steamboat Springs?
There's a place in Vermont, and
you know, even in Western Pennsylvania,
they're getting a ton of snow. I would
explore that. You mentioned that you
were in Florida the other day. I love
Florida.
Spring training has begun. If you don't
know anything about baseball, it'd be
fun to fly to Tampa.
And and check out some of the
some of the spring training teams.
I haven't detected a vulnerability, but
I don't know you well enough yet. But, I
would certainly explore that in
subsequent conversations.
>> So, vulnerability to me, the word is
>> Yeah.
>> kind of
the connotation kind of feels like a
weakness.
>> Yes. It's It's
>> But, it can be both is kind of what
you're
>> Exactly. That's a mistake to think of it
just as a weakness. Think of it as an
opening.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Cuz yeah, like what you were saying is
um
as soon as you mentioned the skiing or
snowboarding, but like yeah, if you were
to be like
I mean, you like snowboarding? Oh my
god, we're we're going to Aspen, and you
could come. I'd be like
>> Exactly.
>> Get out. I'm in.
>> And I'd call a couple of my colleagues,
and I'd say, "Listen, I've got a guy I'm
going to want to develop. He's a
snowboarder. I don't snowboard. You guys
do.
I'm going to tell him we've got a we've
got a thing going. We're going for the
weekend. We happen to have this extra
ticket. It's crazy. What a coincidence?"
>> Mhm.
>> And they'd be all in.
>> Okay, this is very interesting. And how
how could it relate back to cuz this is
where I'm I'm trying to extract
everything CIA related is super
fascinating. And I try to extract it how
can we use it practically in life.
>> Mhm.
>> CIA have access to unlimited amounts of
money and all of these things. Anything
you need like oh, we can get you into
Harvard, blah blah blah.
>> That's the key right there.
>> The normal person doesn't have access to
those things.
>> That's right.
>> So, how might someone else go about
that?
>> Sure, that's a good question. So, I have
a friend who has never been in the CIA,
has never expressed any interest in the
CIA, but he has all the skills of a
successful CIA officer.
And where he has succeeded is as a
fixer.
So, he's in a senior corporate position
now, consulting position.
And
if you are a Hollywood studio
and you want to make a movie in
Cuba
and you can't. We have sanctions on
Cuba.
>> Mhm.
>> But, there's a village in Colombia that
looks just like Havana.
So, he's going to do
all the legwork and you're going to be
able to make your movie in Colombia and
make it look like Cuba. Or
uh
uh I'll give you a real-life example
that he brought me in on.
Um Sacha Baron Cohen wanted to do a
movie called Bruno.
And
my friend was not a Middle East expert
and I am. So, he brought me in. Can you
advise Sacha Baron Cohen on how to make
this movie Bruno? I said, of course. So,
we have an initial meeting and Sacha
says
I want to film this section of the
movie, this portion of the movie in the
Middle East. And I said, great. I said
the Libyans are begging us, this was
under Gaddafi. The Libyans are begging
us to film movies there. They'll give
us, you know, tax-free, they'll pay all
the expenses. He said, don't want to do
it in Libya. He said, as a Jew, I'm I'm
just afraid of going to Libya, I'm
afraid I'll never make it out. I just
don't even want to consider Libya.
And I said, okay, we could do it in
Morocco, but Morocco has very unique
architecture. So, everybody's going to
know that it's Morocco. He to make it
look like,
you know, Syria, Jordan, Israel. But,
everybody's going to They're going to
look at these mud
these mud houses, they're going to say
it's Morocco. It's Moroccan
architecture. It's like, "No, can't do
that." He said, "Let's do it in Jordan."
And I said, "Yeah, but
we could do it in Jordan, but we're
going to have to bring the Jordanian
intelligence service in on it because
they're one of the best services in the
world, and they'll be honest like white
on rice." He said, "Nope.
Can't break cover. Can't break
character.
Don't want to tell the Jordanians."
>> was He's going in
>> When When he's in character, he lives
the character.
>> Right.
>> He's a comedic genius, and I don't use
the word genius lightly. I I've only
worked with a handful of people in my
life that I would consider to be
geniuses. He's a genius.
So,
I said, "That's a mistake."
And I said, "Let's Let's try Syria.
We could do it in Syria."
This is before the [__] hit the fan in
Syria.
>> imagine he'd be frightened cuz Bruno was
He was the big He's very out there gay
guy.
>> Very out there gay guy.
>> [laughter]
>> And then so he's going into countries
>> It didn't work out.
>> Right.
>> So, he said, "Oh, uh I'm going to go to
Newport Beach tomorrow, and there's a
Syrian consulate. I'll just go there."
And I said, "No, no, no." I said,
"Let me do what you're paying me to do.
I'll talk to the Syrian ambassador,
and we'll try to work this out."
He calls me the next night. It was like
midnight. My wife and I were up. I was
reading a book,
and the phone rings. I was like, "It's
midnight. Who could be calling me at
midnight?" And I look, and it's Sacha
Baron Cohen.
And um
and he says, uh He has a very thick
British accent. He says, "Uh John, I
think I [__] up, mate."
And I said, "Oh, I said, "Don't tell me
you went to the Syrian consulate at
Newport Beach."
And he said, "As soon as he walked
through the door, the guy came from
behind the glass partition and said, "I
know who you are. I know what you do.
You are not welcome in Syria."
I said, "Dog gone it.
All right." I said, "Let's Let's try the
Jordanians." So, he said, "No. Let's
just do it. We'll just go to Jordan and
just do it." I said, "I think this is a
serious mistake."
So, what he wanted to do was he wanted
to fly in bonafide terrorists. He He
said in our first conversation,
"Al-Qaeda, Hezbollah."
And he wanted to show them pictures of
men having like hardcore anal sex.
And he wanted to ask them if this
constituted torture and should these men
be sent to Guantanamo.
I said, "That is a terrible idea."
I said, "First, just as a rule of thumb,
you don't want to mess with the
religious types. I said, they'll kill
you. They'll kill your crew. They'll go
on to the street and they'll kill people
who remind them of you."
And I said, "But,
there are bonafide terrorists
who have retired.
They're communists and communism's not
in anymore in Arab nationalism.
So, I said, "These guys all live in
Damascus.
And we could We could fly them into
Amman. But again, we're going to have to
tell the Jordanians what we're doing."
And he said, "No." I said, "Sacha,
listen.
If these bonafide terrorists are all
flying to Jordan on the same day
to come to your hotel room,
they're going to come to the attention
of the intelligence service."
He said, "Won't do it."
So, he and a cameraman flew out
a day before I did.
And
they land in Amman. They get off the
plane, and there's a guy standing there
with a sign.
And it says, "Sacha Baron Cohen."
And he says to the cameraman,
"John, get us a car."
I didn't get him any car.
I'm not a secretary. I'm script advisor.
So,
he says, "I'm Sacha Baron Cohen."
They get in a car, big limousine.
They're driving around.
Finally, it occurs to him,
"This is kind of odd." And he says to
the driver,
"Where are we going?"
And the driver says, "The Royal Palace.
His Majesty's a big fan."
And he says these giant iron gates open
up, they drive onto the palace grounds,
and here is the king himself, and who is
standing next to him but the director
of the Jordanian Intelligence Service.
So, they get out of the car, and the
king says, "Sacha Baron Cohen, I'm your
biggest fan." "Borat?" "I thought I was
going to pee my pants," he says.
"This is the director of the Jordanian
Intelligence Service. Anything you need,
you call him. Welcome to Jordan."
I said, "I told you
before you even landed,
they knew what you were doing.
They're that good."
>> And
>> [clears throat]
>> so, your your friend put that connection
together.
>> Yes.
>> So, you're saying so, he so, one way of
adding big value to people is being a
master connector.
>> That's And that's it. And that's what he
That's what he is. He's a master
connector and a fixer.
>> Mhm.
>> Um
uh
Mission Impossible, you know, four,
whatever it was,
where Tom Cruise wants to do his own
stunts on the outside of the Burj
Khalifa, the biggest building in the
world. You can't do that
unless you're my friend who knows all
the royal families of the United Arab
Emirates and can get the royal family of
Dubai to allow Tom Cruise to be on the
outside of the 105th floor of the Burj
Khalifa. Yeah.
>> Cool. I guess it really pays to network,
eh?
>> It's all about It's all about the
network.
>> Mhm. You're You're making me want to
take acting classes to become that 10%
more extroverted.
>> I'll tell you I'll tell you something
funny.
So, last July, uh a a dear friend of
mine called me.
And [snorts] he's a Hollywood guy.
And he said, "Listen, I wrote a movie,
and you know, this is what the movie's
about. And
I want you to be in my movie. I want you
to act in the movie." And I said, "Oh,
thank you. No. Not interested." I said,
"Thank you for thinking of me. I've
never acted before. I'll be stiff and
unconvincing, and I'm going to wreck
your movie."
And he said,
"I thought of that.
And I thought, 'You know what?
Every day of your CIA career, you acted.
>> Mhm.
>> And you pretended to be somebody that
you weren't.'"
I said, "Well, that's true, actually."
And he said, "I actually wrote the the
role for you."
I said, "Well, who else is in the
movie?" And he names all these people,
and they're all professional actors.
And I said,
"All right. I'll do it." He sends me the
script. I read the script. It's really
good. Like I was I was surprised at how
good it was. To the point where I
introduced him to people that I know on
Broadway, cuz I'm kind of a
networking person, too. And I said,
"This movie takes place all
on one scene. It would make a fantastic
off-Broadway show."
So, I fly to Mexico for the entire month
of October.
And all these actors fly in, and we
spend a month
making this movie.
And
in the end
I get home
and I I come home to my Screen Actors
Guild membership card.
I'm now a professional Hollywood actor.
>> There we go.
>> And um
I saw the first cut of the movie 2 weeks
ago and it's fantastic.
>> tell me what it's called?
>> It's called uh Below World's End.
>> Below World's End.
>> It's going to come out in uh in the
spring.
>> Okay, cool.
>> Yeah.
>> Cool.
>> So
you know, at the CIA the culture is such
that they kind of teach you that
this job is so specific there's nothing
else that you can do.
And that's just simply not true. There's
a lot you can do.
>> That's what I'm learning. I've I've I
didn't even know what the word espionage
meant probably 2 years ago.
Um and I've just been so fascinated on
it all because there's just it's it's
when I look at it cuz I I teach a lot of
just leadership. Like the whole whole
purpose of my company is growing
leaders.
And
when you talk about acting and all this
it's all just flexibility behavior. It's
like how can you be so comfortable being
a gay guy
and then come back home and be a
completely different person. It's like
that flexibility behavior to to
>> Yeah.
>> to change your personality to adapt to
it is just so fascinating.
>> Well, some people would say including
CIA psychiatrists
that this is an example of sociopathic
tendencies.
>> That's what I was going to say to you
actually. Um
what I've heard that sociopaths
they're the ones who they really aren't
picked. But my nails on you
>> Not necessarily.
>> You're not that sociopathic.
>> I'm not. I mean, it's clear.
>> It's probably why you
>> That's why I blew the whistle cuz I'm
not a sociopath.
The CIA actively seeks to hire people
with sociopathic tendencies.
>> So meaning they can dissociate from
feelings.
>> Because they're the good guys.
At least that's what we convince
ourselves of.
With that said, sociopaths, of course,
will slip through the the cracks because
they can blow right through a polygraph
exam and not react to it in any way.
That's That can be dangerous because
usually it's those sociopaths, just like
in the corporate world, who work their
way to the top of the of the ladder
on the backs of the people around them.
>> Mhm.
>> But if you believe that you are the good
guy
and you're doing this for patriotic
reasons
and you can
flip that switch on and off
on your personality
and you're a chameleon where you can
adapt to these different situations
you're going to have a successful career
in espionage.
>> Mhm.
Um [clears throat]
I want to talk about
Epstein.
>> Mhm.
>> Um
as an Australian, I mean, and also just
just in the world of gossip, I'm just
not really involved. I I I see a lot of
stuff and I don't have really strong
opinions on anything. Um but I obviously
see
all this Epstein stuff coming out. Um
my other friend, Andrew Bustamante, he's
also had a similar opinion to you. So,
you you believe Epstein was a spy for a
Mossad.
>> I do. Strongly.
>> What gives you that impression that
you're so certain on that?
>> Oh, it's a lot There's There's a lot of
circumstantial evidence. First of all,
Ghislaine Maxwell's father was a
prolific Mossad spy.
Um that's
>> out there.
>> That's a historic fact. Yes, 100%.
Um
it stands to reason that she would have
introduced him to the Mossad or even her
father would have introduced Epstein to
Mossad.
We don't have any idea where Epstein's
money came from. This is the guy who
never went to college.
And yet he becomes the tax advisor to
the richest man in Ohio
and is referred by the Rothschild
family.
How in the world did that happen?
That's not normal.
Secondly,
one of the things that you're taught
early on
in your
CIA career would be the use of access
agents.
We all want to recruit
the prime minister.
Okay? We're not going to recruit the
prime minister. I don't care how good
you are, how smart you are, how friendly
you are. You're not going to recruit the
prime minister.
See, you do the next best thing. You
recruit the guy who has access to the
prime minister.
If you want to recruit Bill Clinton or
Prince Andrew or Bill Gates or Ehud
Barak. Not not Ehud Barak. That's an
unusual example. I think he was just a
pedophile.
Um
you're not going to recruit Bill Clinton
and then Bill Gates and Prince Andrew.
So,
you recruit a guy who can elicit
information from them.
And then
remember, the Israelis do use coercion.
>> Mhm.
>> Then you wire every room
including the bathrooms for both audio
and video. Just in case you need to
smash somebody over the head
like Peter Mandelson.
>> Who's that?
>> The British ambassador to Washington.
>> Oh, okay.
>> The former British ambassador.
Now he's likely going to be charged with
serious crimes.
>> Um I'm not aware of this. This is a
recent thing that's just come out?
>> Uh Epstein.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Over the last three, four weeks.
Yeah. I mean, it's kind of a long story.
I don't think we have time, but
>> But um yeah, you you recruit the next
best guy.
>> So, so do you think Epstein was a Mossad
agent or recruited as an asset from
Mossad?
>> recruited as an asset.
>> Okay. So, then makes me think
from your judgment, what do you think
would have got him recruited?
>> Money.
>> The lifestyle.
>> Hey, we're going to make you the richest
guy.
>> Yeah.
Sure.
>> do some [__]
>> Private island, the widest townhouse in
Manhattan.
>> I mean, that's pretty good, hey?
>> Yeah.
>> Um so, my opinion on this is
when people ask me um
it's the exact same playbook they used
with Eli Cohen.
Isn't it? So,
>> On a on a bigger on a bigger scale.
>> Yeah. So, I'm like, so you look at So,
Eli Cohen, for those not aware, go and
watch The Spy on Netflix with your
friend in it, Sacha Baron Cohen, which
is a very
very serious role. That's fantastic.
>> story.
>> good.
>> Yeah.
>> Um but, you know, that was I forget the
year that happened, but there was I
don't know, 50, 60, 70, something like
that, right?
>> like 1958
to 1966.
>> [clears throat]
>> Same playbook. We're going to put you in
another country. We're going to make you
an extremely wealthy businessman. Go
throw lavish parties. Here's as much
money as you need.
Get connections everywhere.
And then you got to feed it back all day
long.
>> But, he did it for patriotic reasons.
>> Yes.
>> He did it. He volunteered repeatedly.
But, he was just a barber.
That was his his job. When he first
volunteered to the Mossad, they were
like, "What do you do?" He said, "I'm a
barber,
but I speak Arabic, like really good
Arabic."
And they said, "Yeah, thanks. We're not
interested in recruiting barbers."
And then he kept volunteering.
And finally, they said, "All right, can
you speak in a Syrian accent?" And he
could.
Fluent, flawless Syrian Arabic.
And they said, "Okay, we're going to
send you to Damascus. We're going to
give you money. You're a businessman.
Have big lavish parties and invite
everybody."
>> Mhm.
>> It got to the point where
he was going to
imminently be named
deputy defense minister of Syria.
>> Wow.
>> And here he's an Israeli citizen
and an undercover like deep cover Mossad
agent. And he made one single mistake.
The way he was reporting back to Mossad
was through something called a burst
transmission.
So, what you do is you record all your
information
and
they they give you a radio that's
usually built I mean back in the day it
would be built into a piece of furniture
like a dresser.
So, you record everything into the
dresser, you hit a button, and it sends
out a burst that lasts for a second. And
it just sends all the information back
to your handlers.
It just so happens that there was a KGB
officer in Damascus who said, "You know,
this guy is just a little too slick.
There's something wrong about him."
And they were driving around his
neighborhood with a listening device and
they detected the burst.
And then they went back to the Syrians
and they said, "He's a spy and it's
probably for the Israelis." And they
executed him. They hung him
>> Publicly, yeah.
>> in a public square.
>> But but it's the it's the same they they
run a very similar playbook, right? With
that with the
>> Very much so.
>> Epstein thing. It's like it's
>> And then you just work your way higher
and higher and higher in society.
>> What what I don't get is
um
how do you think
he
persuaded or influenced all of these
people on his island to do all this
[__] up [__]
>> Through his Well, no.
>> Or do you think they just
Like cuz my
>> that they're
perverts.
>> think all of them are?
>> No.
>> Or or do you think maybe like cuz here's
where I'd like I I would see it it could
be a slippery slope. You're out there,
100 people, Bill Gates there, all these
famous celebrities.
I think the chance of some of them being
sickos, high chance.
All of them being sickos?
>> No.
>> That's not That's improbable.
>> was on the Piers Morgan show the other
day with David Boies. David Boies is one
of the most important criminal defense
attorneys in America. Represents Hillary
Clinton, represented Virginia Giuffre.
And he said that
there are thousands and thousands and
thousands of emails between Jeffrey
Epstein and Bill Clinton, between
Jeffrey Epstein and Donald Trump, and
there is zero evidence that either Bill
Clinton or Donald Trump
committed a crime.
So, not not all of them
are perverts. Not all of them implicated
themselves.
Most of them did.
But not all of them.
So, you know, we learned a lot about the
likes of Prince Andrew and, you know,
Sarah Ferguson and Peter Mandelson and
Alan Dershowitz and other like household
names in the United States and the UK.
Most of it was hideous.
Most of them won't be prosecuted for
crimes because the statute of
limitations has expired.
But at least we now know what was going
on at that island or in his giant
mansion in Manhattan.
>> Do you think that was Do you think
Epstein himself
was a sicko or that was perhaps
something that was
>> Oh, no, no. I think that as soon as they
realized what his real vulnerabilities
were, his vulnerabilities were an
absolute love of money
and pedophilia.
>> So, you you Do you think Mossad would
have um
encourage that then or helped
>> Oh, I think it's obvious that they did.
>> So, you're saying they
>> they set him up.
>> helped get underage kids to his island?
>> Oh, of course.
Absolutely.
>> So, they have
no morals.
>> Zero.
>> Is that Mossad or is that an
intelligence agency thing?
>> You know, I think for the most part,
most intelligence agencies have zero
morals. I think that most intelligence
agencies also will draw the line
somewhere.
Like with child sex, for example. That
would never happen at the CIA or at any
other intelligence service that I'm
aware of. And I think the Israelis were
comfortable with it.
>> Do you think he actually killed himself?
>> Yes.
>> Do you So he's Have you seen these
photos popping around of him walking the
streets in Israel?
>> Yeah.
>> The problem is I can't believe anything
online anymore.
>> No. I mean, they're clearly AI-generated
photos. And I saw somebody talking the
other day saying that they were able to
identify it as having been created by
Gemini AI.
>> Why do you think he killed himself and
he wasn't killed?
>> Oh,
>> If he had all of these people
blackmailed.
>> For a for a lot of reasons. First of
all, his life was done.
He was done. He was never going to see
the light of day ever again.
So, do you want to spend the next 40
years in a dank prison? Cuz American
prisons are like third-world prisons.
>> Mhm.
>> Um and I don't think he had the courage
to go through life
for the next 40 years in a in a
maximum-security prison.
Number one.
Uh number two,
I want to address
the reasons that people cite
supporting their belief that he didn't
kill himself.
Um
number one,
the guards all have their heads up their
asses.
The only qualifications to be a prison
guard in the United States
are you have to have the equivalent of a
high school diploma.
You don't even have to have the high
school diploma, just the equivalent of
the high school diploma.
And no felony convictions. Number two,
the cameras never work
in any prison.
>> Really?
>> They never work.
>> Why?
>> When I was in prison, because everybody
has their heads up their asses working
in these prisons. These are retards
working in these prisons. And so, you
know, they're supposed to walk around
every 15 minutes, make sure everything's
okay. Eight minutes walk around every
eight minutes if somebody's on suicide
watch. These guys
they're either, you know, masturbating
in the guard booth
>> The guards?
>> Yeah.
Or they're sound asleep in the guard
booth.
Or they're looking at porn
you know, on the computer. They're not
walking around doing their rounds. And
there's nobody's going to tell them to
get up and go do their rounds. That's
the culture. They're morons. These are
the dregs of society that are prison
guards. Number one.
Number two, the cameras never work. My
job in prison was to be a janitor in the
chapel.
And every time there was a religious
service scheduled I would have to go
into the chapel and break up all these
guys having sex with one another. Why
would they be having sex in the chapel?
Because the cameras didn't work.
And they knew they wouldn't be
interrupted in there. Then people say,
"Oh, if you look closely at the video,
there's a little blip and the camera
Yeah.
Cuz the cameras reset themselves every
night at midnight. And they record over
the previous day's recording. So, it's
not like you stumbled onto some
incredible revelation that, you know,
somebody broke in hacked into the camera
system. No.
>> Mhm.
>> Every camera that works
resets itself.
>> I'm I'm fascinated about your experience
in prison. So, you you're 15 years in
CIA.
Um you
were one of the you were leading on to
bring down one of the biggest
terrorists. I forget his name.
>> Abu Zubaydah.
>> One of the biggest guys.
So, you've been in like, I mean,
probably the most unimaginable place on
Earth having the most strangest, darkest
conversations.
How did you use all these skills when
you first got to prison? What were your
first
>> Oh, I wrote a book about it.
>> Okay. What were What were your first
like 7 days like? How did you scope
people out? What were you assessing?
What
>> Oh. I I said to myself on day one,
"You're trained for this.
>> Uh-huh.
>> You've lived in far worse places than
Loretto, Pennsylvania.
You're going to end up running the
prison."
And so, I wrote a book about this that
that won two literary awards.
>> What's your book called?
>> It's called Doing Time Like a Spy: How
the CIA Taught Me to Survive and Thrive
in Prison.
>> Cool.
>> And I I outlined 20 life lessons that
the CIA taught me and how I applied
those life lessons to prison life. And
the first thing you do is you make
strategic alliances.
So, those alliances were with
the neo-Nazis,
with uh the Italians,
with the Mexican drug cartels,
and with the um Nation of Islam, the the
black Muslims.
>> You made friends with all of them?
>> Every one of them.
>> Do they not hate each other? Or is that
not allowed?
>> hated each other. Like, to the point
where it was potentially deadly.
>> So, would they not
not like you because you're friends with
all of them?
>> I was an independent operator.
I didn't answer to anybody.
>> Did you get
people try to
come and fight you,
persuade you?
>> Never.
Never.
>> know you were inside?
>> They all knew.
Word got around.
>> So, they just probably wouldn't try to
[__] with you.
>> Nobody did.
A couple of times people did, and they
paid dearly for it.
>> What did you do to them?
>> Well, one of the rules in my book
is always let others do your dirty work.
I'll give you an example.
There was a serial killer in my housing
unit.
For reasons that I will never
understand, he took a liking to me.
And he was constantly seeking my
approval.
So,
like he would say things like,
"Hey John, I saved you a seat in the TV
room for the football game." I'd say,
"Thanks, Truck."
We called him Truck because he was a
long-distance truck driver,
and he was murdering prostitutes along
his truck route.
"John, hey, there's a new uh classic
rock station, 16 10 a.m."
"Thanks, Truck."
Well, there was another guy
in the prison we used to call Cat in the
Hat because he had an oddly elongated
head, and he looked like the Cat in the
Hat.
So, he wanted to move into my
my cell.
And we had a rule in our cell, no
pedophiles, right? So, I said, "Are you
a pedophile?" He said, "No." I said,
"What's your crime?" He said, "Murder
for hire." I said, "I'm not sure I like
that much better than pedophiles.
What were the circumstances?"
And he said, "Oh, I was $100,000 in
debt, and I took out an insurance policy
on my business partner, and I hired a
hitman to kill my business partner so I
could cash in the
I said, "Well, that's [__] up.
I don't want you sleeping next to me,
you know, in in the cell."
He was angry.
One day
>> Cuz you didn't let him in.
>> I didn't let him in. One day,
CNN came to the prison to interview me,
and I got called down to the
to the lieutenant's office because the
CNN crew had come to the prison. So,
they say, "Kyriacou, lieutenant's
office." Well, usually people called to
the lieutenant's office are being called
down to rat
and to inform on other people. But,
everybody knew CNN was coming to
interview me that day. Anyway, I'm
sitting next to Truck in the in the TV
room. Cat in the Hat is standing not 3
ft away from me, but he doesn't realize
I'm sitting directly behind him.
And he says to a guy next to him,
"Did you hear Kiriako got called down to
the lieutenant's office? He says that
guy's a [__] rat. He went down there
to rat us all out."
And I didn't react in any way, and Truck
said, "Did you hear that [__] guy?
He just called you a rat."
And I said,
"An hour ago, I heard him call you a
pedophile."
>> [laughter]
>> Which I'd completely made up.
Without saying a word,
Truck got up and beat him to within an
inch of his life.
He was in the hospital for 6 weeks.
Truck got 5 years added to his sentence,
which was 40 years.
And they sent him to a higher security
prison.
Well,
I made sure that Cat in the Hat heard
why he had gotten such a beating.
And when he came back from the hospital
after 6 weeks,
he came up to me and he said,
with his head down, "I'm so sorry I
called you a rat. I should never have
said anything. I apologize."
And I said,
"I'm going to tell you one thing and
then I'm never going to say anything
again.
If I ever hear my name cross your lips
ever again,
you're dead.
Understand?"
And he said, "Yes."
So, nobody Nobody [__] [laughter] with
me in prison.
>> Uh
Uh so,
I want to get your book. I didn't know
you had That that's that's amazing. You
don't have any hard copies around there?
>> but I'll tell you what, it's done so
well that Simon and Schuster just came
out with a second edition.
>> Oh, amazing. I'm going to get my hands
on it. Um
So, how how can Cuz as you're saying all
that, the number one thing I'm feeling
in my body is how much confidence you
have to go into those situations.
And I imagine a lot of people watching
this
could apply that to their life. Like
maybe they're just starting a new job or
they're I don't know, new friend group
or whatever it might be and they're in a
situation where they're like, I feel
like
uncomfortable here. Yes. What what's the
first kind of go-to to actually come
back
>> Have confidence in yourself. I worked
with a guy. When I left the agency, this
guy came up to me, who I liked.
He was kind of an assistant. He wasn't
an ops officer, but he he shook my hand.
He said, "I'm going to miss you. It's
been fun working with you." I said, "Oh,
you're great. I'm going to miss you,
too." Genuinely good guy.
And he said, "I want to tell you how
much I admire you." And I said, "Oh,
thank you. That's so nice of you to
say." He said, "I admire you because out
of everybody I've met here,
you're the only one who's not afraid of
anybody."
And I said, "Yeah, you know what?" I
said,
"I'm not.
I'm not afraid of anybody. And I don't
really know why that is."
When I got back from Pakistan, even my
mother said to me,
"Were you afraid
like breaking down these doors and
grabbing these Al-Qaeda people?"
And I said, "No. I said, you know, I
think it's because I was so busy
that I just didn't have time to really
process the emotion of fear.
I just didn't think about it. But then
in retrospect,
I don't know. Maybe there's just some
switch in my brain that never activated
a sense of fear.
I I don't really have an explanation for
it.
>> So, even in the beginning, your your
first job or anything like that, there
was never a sense of
"Shit, this could go wrong."
>> No. I have been intimidated a couple of
times.
>> On the job?
>> Yeah, like
I'd been on the job 8 months.
August 2nd, 1990.
I get to the office. Iraq has just
invaded Kuwait.
I get to the office early and my boss
says, "Don't take your jacket off. We're
going to the White House."
I'd never been to the White House
before. We get in a car, drive to the
White House. A Marine escorts us into
the Oval Office. It's the President, the
Vice President, the National Security
Advisor, the CIA Director, my boss and
me.
>> Who was the president then?
>> George H.W. Bush.
We all sit down and the President says,
"Well,
now what do we do?"
And then everybody turns and looks at
me.
I was 25 years old.
And I'm looking at him like
And then it took me a second like, "Oh.
Oh. Uh yes. Well, Mr. President, as you
know, Iraqi troops crossed the border at
2:00 this morning. They've taken the
whole of Kuwait. The royal family has
fled to Saudi Arabia.
Et cetera, et cetera.
I was intimidated. I'd never met a
president before.
You know? And not only am I meeting the
President and the Vice President and the
CIA Director and the National Security
Advisor, but they're asking for my
advice on issues of war and peace. I'm
25 years old.
So, that was intimidating.
>> But do you think do you think your
confidence comes
from cuz I mean, when you become in the
CIA, you would have spent time training
at the farm.
>> Sure.
>> Do you think after that, you would have
come out there being like, "I'm one of
the most trained [__] people across
the board on multiple different facets?"
>> Yes.
>> And then you go into say somewhere like
prison, you're like, "There's not one
person here
>> Yes.
>> who's as smart as equipped as me."
>> You you've heard of imposter syndrome.
Yeah. I never experienced that.
>> Mhm.
>> No.
No. I thought, well,
I'm as smart as these guys.
>> That's very fascinating. So,
one of um
one Do you know Chase Hughes?
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah, so he's a good friend of mine, and
that's one of the big things he's
talks about and teaches me. He's like
He's like, "I can teach you all the
skills." He's like, "All the scripts,
this things." Like, "But if you don't
have that confidence
>> Exactly.
>> to do it."
And my whole understanding of confidence
comes from actually just building
evidence. So,
>> Yes.
>> Um I do Every time I come out to America
here, I'll I'll tell you more about off
this, but we'll do like fun stuff like
combat training and blah blah blah.
>> Sure.
>> And every every time I do it, I leave
there feeling like more confident. I'm
like, "Wow." Like, and I grew up in a in
a boxing gym. I grew up doing Muay Thai
and stuff. So, throughout my sort of
teenage life and early 20s, I felt a
little bit of confidence, you know, on
the streets and whatever. But this is
taking it to a whole other level, where
I'm like, it ends You know, so
I I guess what I'm trying to extract
from you is if the people listening to
this want to leave here and go, "How can
I build my own confidence?" Have you got
any advice of what either you've gone
through or what you've even had to deal
with people in the field? I'm sure you
probably had to recruit people and put
them in uncomfortable situations.
>> Sure.
>> How do you quickly develop confidence in
someone?
>> You have to throw yourself right into
the middle of it. And don't be afraid to
fail.
Fail a lot. That's how you learn. I I
sat next to a guy in Arabic training for
a year, right? 9 hours a day, 5 days a
week for an entire year. It was only
three of us in the class. So, I sat next
to this guy. Good-looking guy, really
athletic, and had a gift for the Arabic
language.
And his dad had been the Deputy Director
of the CIA, right? This guy has
everything going for him.
And I remember thinking, "Man, this guy
is a really great officer." It was a
pleasure to know him.
So, I went out to the Middle East. He
went to the very neighboring country.
And
he sends me a classified email one day.
And he said, "What are you doing this
weekend?" I said, "Nothing, actually."
He said, "Can you fly over here?"
And I thought, "Huh, that's odd." I
said, "Sure."
So, it's like a 30-minute flight from
one country to the next. I fly down
there. He picks me up at the airport. I
said, "Are you okay?"
And he said, "No." He said, "This job is
not for me. It's not." I said, "Are you
kidding me?"
>> He was a spy?
>> Yeah.
>> For CIA or
>> Yeah, CIA.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> Yeah, we were in Arabic together.
>> Okay, yeah, yeah.
>> So, I said, "You're a natural-born case
officer." He said, "I don't have it in
my heart to convince people to commit
treason. I can't do it."
And I said, "You have a conscience." And
he said, "My dad's going to be so
ashamed. I don't even know how to tell
him." And I said, "No, man, you tried."
I said, "There are a million other
things you can do. You're a gifted
linguist, and you're a nice guy."
So,
we had dinner at his place that night.
His girlfriend was living with him. And
we we had a long heart-to-heart. And
sort of talked through the whole thing.
And I said, "Don't worry about your dad.
Your dad loves you. Your dad doesn't
care if you're not going to be a case
officer. Your dad doesn't care if you're
not going to, you know, be a deputy
director of the CIA like like he was.
Your dad wants you to be happy.
That's all. Every dad wants his son to
be happy." I had kids at the time. He
didn't have kids.
And so,
he called his dad and he said, "This
this is not for me." And his dad said,
"What do you think would be for you?"
And he said, "I want to be a nurse."
And his dad said, "Resign and come home
and be the best nurse you can be."
And that's what he's doing. He's a
nurse. And he's happy.
>> I mean, yeah, that that heart that that
value system definitely wouldn't work.
I want to help people.
Um, what would you say is the number one
spy skill
people should have in everyday life?
>> Adaptability.
We shouldn't be so laser-focused on
ourselves and our needs
that we can't see what other people need
or what other people respond to.
You know, always be thinking about other
people.
>> What's your What's your status on the
whole CIA and everything now? So, you've
you've been out of jail for When did you
get out of jail?
>> Uh, February of 2015.
>> Okay, so wow. So, 11 years now.
>> Are friends with anybody in the agency
still?
>> oh, yeah. Lots.
>> Okay, so there's Is there bad blood
there?
>> No.
>> Are you worried? Well, I mean, 11 years,
you're probably not worried anymore.
>> No, listen, I'm very
>> when you got out?
>> Yeah, a little bit. I'm very popular at
the CIA now.
>> Okay.
>> Because my detractors are all either
dead or retired. History has smiled on
me. I was right and they were wrong.
It's as simple as that.
>> So, you were Was there a Was there a
period there where you were worried that
you would end up on hit lists?
>> No.
>> Even in jail?
My My attorneys warned me
just before I went to prison that
the CIA was very upset that my sentence
was so short.
>> Mhm.
>> And he He My attorney said, "They're
going to try to set you up in there.
So, be very, very careful."
And that was at the front of my mind. I
was in I was in about 3 months
and there was an Afghan-American
prisoner in there. He was a pharmacist
who had an oxy problem.
And he came up to me one day and he
said, "Hey, John, there's a new guy who
wants to meet you."
I said, "Yeah, who's that?" He said, "He
was the spokesman for the Taliban."
I said, "That guy from New Jersey?
He said, "Yeah."
I said, "No, I don't want to meet I
don't want to meet him."
And he said, "Oh, okay. I'll tell him."
Couple days later, I'm out in the prison
yard
exercising
and this
guy with a beard halfway to his waist
is walking right up to me with his hand
out to shake my hand.
And I put my hands up like this and I
said, "Don't [__] touch me."
And just as I said it, I looked past him
and there was a guard
in the woods outside the fence with a
camera with a long-distance lens. Click
click click click click click click. And
I said, "Don't [__] touch me. I said,
I will kill you if you try to touch me."
And he said, "Come on, man. I just want
to be friends." I said, "Fuck you. I
don't want to be your friend. Get the
[__] out of here." And he says, "You and
I have a lot in common." I said, "You
and I have nothing in common other than
that I tried to kill people like you.
Get the [__] out of here."
And then he walked away, but I never put
my hands down cuz I wanted to make sure
that the guards' pictures all showed me
not touching him.
>> Mhm.
>> And so, um
he walked away. He was only in the
prison for 4 days.
So, they transferred him in just to set
me up.
And then I saw the guard later. He was
from the lieutenant's office and I said,
"Nice try, amateur."
>> [laughter]
>> And that was it.
>> Oh.
So fun. Um John, we've we've
come to the end. Um where can everyone
find you? Like what are you doing now?
Like where's your like where can
everyone find you? Where can they get
your book and and what's your mission
now?
>> Um you know, I have found kind of a
second life in podcasting. I've got
three successful monetized podcasts
right now. One is every day Monday
through Friday on YouTube and Rumble.
It's called Deprogram. We talk about the
news every day. I've got one that drops
twice a week called Deep Focus, which is
more in-depth interviews with activists,
attorneys, politicians, people like
that.
And then I've got a very, very popular
one on Apple Podcasts.
Actually, I just talked to the producer.
He just tried to call me a second ago.
I I'm ranked seventh in the world this
week. It's called John Kiriakou's Dead
Drop. And it's like all the stories from
my career.
>> Okay.
>> And um
and I just sent my ninth book to the
publisher.
Uh so I've got a lot of books out there.
And uh
yeah, I mean it's
it's a little bit of this, a little bit
of that.
And I I've put together a handsome
living.
>> I love it. Where where can everyone get
your books?
>> Oh, they're all on Amazon. Or the first
one's out of print now, but the rest are
all on Amazon.
>> What what's the the one the 20 practical
things again?
>> Yeah, that's uh Doing Time Like a Spy.
>> That one's still in print?
>> I want to get that one.
>> Thank you so much.
>> to get it. Um beautiful. So to wrap this
up, final question for you.
If you were to go back to your
18-year-old self and give him 30 seconds
of advice, what would it be? Hey, real
quick. Just before we wrap up this
episode, DreamFest is just around the
corner, okay? And if you have not yet
jumped on the waitlist or got yourself a
ticket, every single thing you need to
know about it is in the link below. So
go ahead and hit that, secure your spot,
check out everything that we've got
going on this year. You're going to
freaking love it. This is going to be
the thing that's going to take you from
where you are to where you want to get
to. So hit the link, check it all out.
Now let's get back into this interview.
>> That's that's a tough one. You know, I
think it would be the advice that I'd
give
any younger person today
is to be true to yourself and to trust
your gut on issues of right and wrong.
We all We all know deep down
what's right and what's wrong.
Do what's right.